Finding Aid for Jim Dunne papers, 1969-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jim Dunne papers 1969-2011, 1974-1996
Dunne, Jim, 1931-
(in 4 boxes)
2 linear feet
2012071 Aa 2
Jim Dunne is known for his work as a pioneer in automotive spy photography. He is also an established journalist and author, and conducted automotive performance tests and reviews of new vehicles for many years. The collection, spanning 1969-2011, includes his book Car Spy: Secret Cars Exposed by the Industry's Most Notorious Photographer, magazines containing his photographic work, articles written by him, and awards and recognitions. A large portion of the collection is made up of visual materials, which consists of photographs, slides, negatives, CDs containing images of automobiles he included in his book, and a digital slideshow presentation featuring his work.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group was donated by Jim Dunne (donor no. 10693 ) on November 30, 2011. Additional materials were received on February 2, 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Jim Dunne is an automotive spy photographer and journalist. He is notorious among automobile manufacturers world-wide because he spent forty years taking and publishing photos of future automobile models well before their intended public introduction. His skills stem from his service in the Army where he was NCO in charge of an infantry intelligence and reconnaissance squad. Although his career has led to his photograph being featured on "Wanted!" posters in several proving ground security offices, some places pay ironic tribute to his enthusiasm and skill by making him the namesake for places like "Dunne's Grove" at the GM proving grounds in Milford, Michigan.
Mostly known mostly for his spy photography, Dunne was also a well-established journalist. He was a columnist for Popular Science, writer, and Detroit editor of Popular Mechanics for 21 years, and editor of the Motor Camping Handbook and Road and Track magazine. He was also Director of the Auto Writers League of Detroit (AWL). In 2011 he published an autobiographical book, entitled Car Spy: Secret Cars Exposed by the Industry's Most Notorious Photographer, which details the ins and outs of automotive spy photography and features over 200 images he has taken throughout his career.
Since Dunne's writing mostly focused on the developments in auto industry and business, and their effects, particularly in Detroit, his career also involved automotive testing. For thirteen years he conducted on-track testing of new vehicles to examine differences in performance between models. His methods are still used in most national car magazine track testing reviews.
Throughout his career, Jim Dunne has taken thousands of photographs, and written many articles that have been featured on radios and televisions, and in magazines and newspapers around the world. In 2006, he received the International Automotive Media Award for Lifetime Achievement. He also received the 2007 Road & Travel Magazine's 4th Annual Lifetime Achievement Award.
The Jim Dunne collection mostly consists of publications and visual materials from across his career, including articles written by and about him, photographs, negatives, and some digital materials. The series in this collection are: Publications, Visual Materials, Recognitions, and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Dunne, Jim, 1931-; Automobile driving.; Automobile industry and trade--United States.; Automobiles.; Automobiles.; Automotive journalists.; Experimental automobiles.; Photographers--Michigan--Biography.; Photographers--United States--Biography.; Photography of automobiles.
Genre Terms:
CD-ROMs.; Photographs.
- Publications
  The Publications include articles, books, and magazines in which Dunne was credited for his journalistic or photographic work. These include many Car Test and Driving Reports he wrote for Popular Science, several issues of Auto Week, in which he is credited for his photography, and some issues of the Motor Camping Handbook, of which he was an editor and also writer. Among other miscellaneous publications for which he wrote, or did photography, is also a copy of his autobiographical book, Car Spy: Secret Cars Exposed by the Industry's Most Notorious Photographer.
  - Articles
    - Popular Science
      - Car Test and Driving Report
        - 1974 (Box 1)
        - 1978 (Box 1)
        - 1979 (Box 1)
        - 1980 (Box 1)
        - 1981 (Box 1)
        - 1982 (Box 1)
        - 1983 (Box 1)
        - 1984 (Box 1)
  - Books
    - Car Spy: Secret Cars Exposed by the Industry's Most Notorious Photographer, 2011 (Box 1)
  - Magazines
    - Auto Week
      - June 30, 1980 (Box 4)
      - October 13, 1980 (Box 4)
      - May 6, 1985 (Box 4)
      - June 29, 1987 (Box 1)
      - April 29, 1991 (Box 1)
      - April 26, 1993 (Box 1)
      - October 28, 1996 (Box 1)
      - May 5, 2003 (Box 1)
      - December 26, 2011 (Box 1)
        (includes an advertisement on pg 53 for his book Car Spy: Secret Cars Exposed by the Industry's Most Notorious Photographer)
    - Motor Camping Handbook
      - 1974 (Box 1)
      - 1975 (Box 1)
      - 1976 (Box 1)
      - 1977 (Box 1)
      - 1978 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Business Week, May 3, 1993 (Box 1)
      - Consumer Guide Auto Series -- Car Preview 1986-87, September 1985 (Box 1)
        (includes a letter from Publications International Ltd. regarding shots used for this issue)
      - Ward's Auto World, October 1994 (Box 1)
      - Wheels, August 1987 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series includes a press release from the Auto Writers League of Detroit, a Trespass Statement regarding the GM Proving Grounds, a letter regarding a profile written about Jim Dunne, and several magazine photo clippings for which Dunne was credited. There is also a reproduction of the first issue of The Horseless Age, a publication that recorded the transition from horse-drawn transportation to automotive transportation.
  - Auto Writers League of Detroit (AWL) (Box 1)
    (press release, undated)
  - GM Proving Grounds Trespass Statement August 27, 1991 (Box 1)
  - The Horseless Age, Vol. 1 No. 1, November 1895 Reproduction (Box 1)
  - Letter regarding a profile written about Jim Dunne November 27, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Magazine Photo Clippings (Box 1)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials make up a majority of the collection, consisting of photographs, slides, and negatives of various sizes. Most of the material is organized chronologically, or alphabetically by label, if the information was provided. Some materials are also organized categorically, such as black and white photos, color photos, and personal photos, in which Dunne and his colleagues are the subjects. The series also includes several CDs that contain a presentation highlighting Jim Dunne's work, and digital copies of photographs compiled for his book.
  - CDs
    - Car Spy Photos
      - 435 Photos by Jim Dunne November 2011 (Box 1)
      - All 231 Images -- Not All Numbered 11/17/2010 (Box 1)
      - 1st Group -- 1st 70 Photos with numbers 11/18/2010 (Box 1)
      - 2nd Group -- 62 Photos with numbers 11/18/2010 (Box 1)
      - 3rd Group -- 55 70 Photos with numbers 11/18/2010 (Box 1)
      - 4th Group -- 42 70 Photos with numbers 11/18/2010 (Box 1)
      - Chapters 1-3, Intro with Numbers 12/10/1910 (Box 1)
      - Chapters 4-7 with Numbers 12/10/1910 (Box 1)
      - Chapters 8-9 with Numbers 12/10/1910 (Box 1)
      - Chapters 10-13 with Numbers 12/10/1910 (Box 1)
    - Jim Dunne Presentation December 7, 2007, 1 optical disks DVDs 8:33 min. (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Black and White 1960s-1980s (Box 1)
    - Color, 1960s-2000s, 2 folders (Box 1)
      (various sizes)
    - Envelopes
      (some envelopes include negatives; identifications are Dunne's)
      - Dated
        - 1969 Photos -- Inside Ford, Pontiac Basement (Box 1)
          (envelope # 1)
        - 1980 Chevrolet Caprice Classic (Box 1)
          (envelope # 2)
        - 1980 Ford Pickup Truck (Box 1)
          (envelope # 3)
        - 1980 Ford Thunderbird (Box 1)
          (envelope # 4)
        - 1980 Lincoln Continental Sedans (Box 1)
          (envelope # 5)
        - 1980 Lincoln Mark VI (Box 1)
          (envelope # 6)
        - 1980 Mercury Cougar XR-7 (Box 1)
          (envelope # 7)
        - 1980 Oldsmobile Delta 88 (Box 1)
          (envelope # 8)
        - 1980 Pontiac Grand Safari (Box 1)
          (envelope # 9)
        - 1997 Corvette Cormaro (Box 1)
          (envelope # 10)
        - 1999 Mustang, Lincoln LS (Box 1)
          (envelope # 11)
        - Shot in 2000 (Box 1)
          (envelope # 12)
        - 2000 Valrey (?), Mercedes SL, Liberty (Box 1)
          (envelope # 13)
        - Summer 2001 Summer 2002 (Box 1)
          (envelope # 14)
        - Summer 2003 Aston Martin, Mercedes SL, Dodge Magnum, Corvert (?), Chevy Colorado (Box 1)
          (envelope # 15)
        - Dodge Magnum 2005 Mercedes Coupe 2004 BMW G-Series (Box 1)
          (envelope # 16)
        - 2005 BMW 6, M-B 500 Coupe (Box 1)
          (envelope # 17)
        - 2005 Corvette (Box 1)
          (envelope # 18)
        - Magnum 2005 at Ranchette (Box 1)
          (envelope # 19)
        - 2005 Mustang, Freestyle, Five Hundred (Box 1)
          (envelope # 20)
      - Undated
        - 23 GM Van (Box 1)
          (envelope # 21)
        - Clean LS, Porky Chrysler Van/Chrysler Van, Continental, Riviera with Spats, C5s Vette (Box 1)
          (envelope # 22)
        - Mercedes (Box 1)
          (envelope # 23)
        - Mercury Milan, SUV covered (Box 1)
          (envelope # 24)
    - Minox Film and Photographs -- Pontiac Basement: Ford, Chevy Inside March 1970 (Box 1)
    - Personal, 1970s-1990s (Box 1)
      (includes black and white and color photos)
  - Negatives
    - Various Sizes (Box 1)
    - 35mm Film
      - Saxton and Fusion and Crossover (Box 2)
      - Shots from 1995 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
        (7 folders, 3 envelopes)
  - Slides (Box 3)
    (4 folders)
- Awards and Recognitions
  The Recognitions consist of publications that feature Jim Dunne, such as "Drive-by Shooting," an article written in Esquire's September 1997 American Scene column. Many of these publications pay tribute to Dunne as being the first automotive spy photographer, giving him the nickname "Dunne 007" for his James Bond-style methods. There is also an event program from the 16th International Automotive Media Awards, in which Jim Dunne was honored as the recipient of the International Automotive Media Award for Lifetime Achievement.
  - 16th International Automotive Media Awards event program December 18, 2006 (Box 4)
    (features Jim Dunne as the recipient of the International Automotive Media Award for Lifetime Achievement)
  - American Way, November 15, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Esquire, September 1997 (Box 4)
  - Gross Pointe News Vol. 62 No. 50, December 13, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Highway -- Malaysia, August 1998 (Box 4)
    (includes a letter and page proofs from Chips Yap regarding the article written about him)
  - Hour Detroit, January 2006 (Box 4)
  - Photo District News (PDN), October 2006 (Box 4)
  - Road & Travel Magazine article -- Jim Dunne to Receive Lifetime Achievement Award at 2007 International Car of the Year Awards, November 6, 2006 (Box 4)
  - The Toronto Star article-- Auto Show '91 -- Legendary Auto Spy Exposes Motor City's Styling Secrets: Jim Dunne Photographs Cars You Aren't Supposed to See, February 12, 1991 (Box 4)